<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="file:/home/lou/Public/TEIslides/teislides.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Text formats and how to handle them</title>
                <author>Lou Burnard Consulting</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unpublished draft</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>born digital</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2019-09-21">Created file</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="slide">
                <head>Silk purses and sow's ears</head>
                <list>
                    <item>Can you make a silk purse out of a sow's ear? <list>
                            <item>(or, in French, faire d'une buse un epervier)?</item>
                            <item>(or, in Italian, la botte dà il vino che ha non si cava sangue da
                                una rapa)</item>
                            <item>or, maybe, in Russian, из говна конфетку не сделаешь
                                <!--Не родит верба
                        груши.--></item>
                        </list></item>
                    <item>Documents come in many different formats, but these formats are usually
                        intended to represent a common set of features.</item>
                    <item>Given the right tools and a common set of features, we should be able to
                        convert (transduce) from one format representing a given set of features to
                        another representation using a different format.</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="box">Up to a point...</p>
            </div>
            <div type="slide">
                <head>Semantic vs presentational features</head>
                <list>
                    <item>Some formats aim to capture semantic features of a document ("heading",
                        "paragraph", "title") </item>
                    <item>Others aim to specify the way a document should be formatted ("font size",
                        "justification", "italic"...)</item>
                    <item>and in many/most the distinction is not clear : for example, what does
                            <gi>p</gi> mean in HTML? or <gi>br</gi> ? </item>
                </list>
            </div>
            <div type="slide">
                <head>We are where we are</head>
                <p>Documents might come in... </p>
                <list>
                    <item>so-called PVA -- plain text with no encoding</item>
                    <item>plain text with esoteric codes</item>
                    <item>Word or ODT : word processor formats</item>
                    <item>(X)HTML or eBook : web formats</item>
                    <item>Typesetting formats (inDesign, TeX...)</item>
                    <item>XML or TEI-XML </item>
                    <item>PDF </item>
                </list>

            </div>
            <div type="slide">
                <head>Low hanging fruit...</head>
                <list>
                    <item>A PDF file preserves only the appearances of an original: you can
                        (painfully sometimes) extract letters from it by clever programming, but
                        it's usually quicker to just print it out, and put it through an OCR
                        process</item>
                    <item>A TEI-XML document should come with an ODD defining its use of the TEI
                        vocabulary: use that to help you write an XSLT stylesheet to extract just
                        the elements and attributes you want </item>
                    <item>Plain text : as you've seen, it may be quite easy to add minimal TEI
                        tagging, provided that the text is consistent in e.g. its use of linebreaks,
                        whitespace, capitals, and other things that your regular expressions will be
                        relying on</item>
                </list>
            </div>
            <div type="slide">
                <head>Word or Libre Office vel sim</head>
                <list>
                    <item>These are in fact XML formats respecting (more or less) the OOXML standard
                        ... up to a point</item>
                    <item>A Word file is really a compressed archive, like a zip, containing
                        numerous document fragments </item>
                    <item>oXygen can unpack and transform the useful part into TEI for you</item>
                    <item>Word <term>styles</term> are preserved : so if they were used semantically
                        in the original, converting them to semantic tagging is easy</item>
                    <item>But there are always surprises...</item>
                </list>
            </div>
            <div type="slide">
                <head>XHTML and friends</head>
                <list>
                    <item>HTML looks superficially like XML, but is not necessarily well-formed and
                        rarely validated</item>
                    <item>XHTML is an XML-conformant expression of HTML: use the invaluable
                            <ident>tidy</ident> utility to generate it</item>
                    <item>eBooks, like docx, are really compressed archives containing many
                        different XHTML or other files </item>
                    <item>The organization of an ebook is more or less well-standardized but because
                        the focus of the encoding is snazzy presentation, there is much variation,
                        for example in style names and behaviours</item>
                </list>
            </div>
            <div type="slide">
                <head>Typesetting and other esoteric formats</head>
                <list>
                    <item> You may encounter legacy type-setting formats such as TeX or
                        inDesign</item>
                    <item>These formats represent the desired formatting of the text, but not
                        (usually) its semantics </item>
                    <item>Conversion from XML to these formats is useful and fairly straightforward
                        (there is also a standard called DSSSL of relevance here); the reverse is
                        not the case </item>
                </list>
                <p rend="box">Good luck!</p>
            </div>
            <div type="slide">
                <head>Two essential technologies: regexp and xpath</head>
                <p>Regexp (regular expressions) allow you to specify <term>patterns</term> which
                    match strings of characters and manipulate the resulting matches <list>
                        <item><code>xyz</code> : the string xyz</item>
                        <item><code>[xyz]</code> any one of the characters x y z</item>
                        <item><code>[\d+]</code> one or more digits</item>
                        <item><code>[\p{Lu}+]</code> one or more uppercase unicode characters</item>
                    </list></p>
                <p>Xpath is a standard syntax for matching parts of an XML tree in terms of its
                    elements and attributes <list>
                        <item><code>//p</code> : any <gi>p</gi> anywhere</item>
                        <item><code/><code>//p[anchor] </code>: any <gi>p</gi> containing an
                                <gi>anchor</gi></item>
                        <item><code>//p[@rend] </code> : any p with a <att>rend</att>
                            attribute</item>
                        <item><code>//p[starts-with(@rend,'Head')]</code> any p whose
                                <att>rend</att> attribute has a value starting with
                            <val>Head</val></item>
                    </list></p>
                <p>Regexp and xpath are both built-in to oXygen</p>
            </div>
            <div type="slide">
                <head>Programming options</head>
                <p>If you have lots of texts in a specific arcane format, it is worth investing time
                    and effort to translate them, using whatever tools are at your disposal. </p>
                <p>A multi-stage path is usually easiest, e.g. <list><item>use tidy, or perl or python or whatever
                    language you like to convert to well-formed xml</item><item>use XSLT to convert
                    arbitrary XML to TEI ELTeC</item></list></p>
                <p rend="box"> Remember: the computer should be doing the boring repetitive work, not you!</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>

</TEI>
