<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="file:/home/lou/Public/TEIslides/teislides.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Getting started</title>
            <author>Lou Burnard Consulting</author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt><p>unpublished draft</p></publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc><p>born digital</p></sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2019-09-14">Created file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
    <text xml:id="tutorial-hdr"><body  >
     <div type="slide">
         <p>This tutorial shows you how to create an ELTeC level zero file, and how to complete the
        metadata required by the TEI Header. </p></div>
      <div type="slide"> <head>Getting started</head> <list>
            <item>Open oXygen and click on the New icon (first left on the toolbar); or
                select File->New from the menu; or type CTRL-N</item>
            <item>The New File dialogue appears. Under the heading <ident>Global
                templates</ident>, you should see the template for ELTeC-0. Select it.
                (If it's not there, you need to tweak your installation of oXygen; or you
                can simply open the template file <ident>ELTeC-0.xml</ident> from your Work
                directory). </item><item>Change the filename in the bottom of the window from
                    <ident>Untitled.xml</ident> or <ident>ELTeC-0</ident> to something more
                    appropriate: we suggest using the identifier for the file you're planning to
                    work on. Either way...</item>
            <item>... the main oXygen editing window opens, with the beginnings of an ELTeC
                XML file in it. Note the following: <list>
                    <item>At the top of the file there are two purple lines beginning
                        <code>&lt;?xml-model</code>.</item>
                    <item>The file contains tags (in blue) and attribute names (in orange)
                        and helpful comments (in green) ... but no text other than some bits of the header.</item>
                    <item>To the right of the main window there is a status bar with an
                        angry red square at the top and some red error flags. These
                        correspond with parts of the text display underlined in red.</item>
                    <item>Underneath the editing window there is an error message
                        corresponding with the first error flag: <code>value of attribute
                            "xml:id" is invalid; must be an XML name without colons
                        </code></item>
                </list></item>
            <item>The red flags tell us that although oXygen has done its best some
                additional information is needed to create a valid header. Let's
                fix up some of these errors!</item>
        </list>
    </div>   
        <div type="slide">
            <head>Making the header valid</head>
            <list>
                <item>The schema requires a proper value for @xml:id but we have not yet
                    supplied one. Put the cursor between the quote marks and type in the
                    identifier for your novel<!--, e.g. <code>POL002</code> if you've chosen to work
                    on <ident>beczkowska_bedzie_1897.txt</ident>-->. A new error message appears!
                    <code>element "TEI" missing required attribute "xml:lang"</code>. </item>
                <item>Put the cursor before the &gt; at the end of the <gi>TEI</gi> start-tag
                    and type a space to see the available attributes. <att>xml:lang</att>
                    appears in the list in bold because it's required here. Select it, and then
                    add the language code for your
                    document. </item>
                <item>The next red line is complaining about the content of the <gi>measure</gi>
                    element at line 17, which should contain a number indicating how many words the
                    text contains. If you don't know the wordcount for your text, you can enter 
                    any number you like for the moment, but don't forget to count the words in your text and
                    correct this when you've finished! Note that the count is supplied as content of an element, not an attribute
                    value. </item>
                <item>The next three red lines are all to do with the text classification codes.
                    You need to decide what value to enter for the "authorGender" category (M,
                    F, or U); what size code corresponds with the word count ('short', 'medium',
                    or 'long'); and what time slot code (T1,T2,T3 or T4) is applicable. You have
                    the data: refer to the header documentation (for example <ref
                        target="https://github.com/distantreading/WG1/wiki/teiHeaders">on the
                        wiki</ref>) for a reminder on what the codes mean.</item>
                <item>To remove the only remaining red line in the header, enter today's date,
                    in the right (YYYY-MM-DD) format as value for the <att>when</att> attribute.
                    Phew! no red marks anywhere in the Header -- which is now therefore valid:
                    click the disk icon (or type CTRL-S, or choose File-Save from the menu) to
                    save it for further work. </item>
                <item>This is a good start, but validity is not necessarily the same thing as
                    truth, and we would prefer our document to be true -- the title of this work
                    is definitely not <code>Title</code>, and your name is not <code>Your Name
                        Here</code>! More seriously, we have not yet provided any information at
                    all about the source from which this ELTeC text derives nor about its
                    author. Over to you... Referring to the metadata you accumulated
                    in the first part of this exercise, you should now add the following: <list>
                        <item>the actual title of the novel</item>
                        <item>the author's name and dates in the recommended format</item>
                        <item>an additional <gi>respStmt</gi> to show who was responsible for
                            the original data capture of this title (if you know)</item>
                        <item>the date of publication of this digital version (today!)</item>
                        <item>information about the source as described below</item>
                    </list></item>
                <item>The source description should contain two <gi>bibl</gi> elements, one
                    (with <att>type</att>
                    <code>digitalSource</code>) for the digital source from which your version
                    derives, and one (with <att>type</att>
                    <code>firstEdition</code>) for the first print edition of this work. Without
                    a lot of detective work, it's hard to tell whether this text was transcribed
                    from the first edition, or via some intermediate modern edition, but if you
                    are reasonably sure that a modern edition is the actual source, you could
                    supply a third <gi>bibl</gi> with information about it.</item>
              
                <item>Your research should have provided you with enough information to provide
                    a basic bibliographic description of the first edition of the novel,
                    including for example publisher name, place of publication, as well as the
                    original published title and form of the author's name, which might differ
                    from the versions in use today. At the very least, your <tag>bibl
                        type="firstEdition"</tag> should contain a <gi>date</gi> giving the year
                    of first publication. </item>
            </list>
            <p>When you're happy with your header, and it has no redlines, remember to save the file
                before proceeding to add something to the <gi>body</gi> element!
            </p>
        </div>
    </body></text>
</TEI>
