<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>Sampling criteria for the ELTeC</title>
    <author>COST Action CA16204 – WG1 </author>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2018-01</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <p>Unpublished discussion document prepared for COST Action 16204</p>
   </publicationStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <p>Converted from a Word document</p>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change><date>2020-07-09</date> LB tinkered a bit following discussion of the EC5</change><change><date>2019-01-28</date> CO revised the criteria; removed outdated use cases.</change>
   <change><date>2018-01-30</date> LB revised table; added some discussion to criteria; tarted up
    bibliog </change>
   <change><date>2018-01-27</date> LB converted to XML</change>
   <change><date>2018-01-27</date> CO Final draft</change>
   <change><date>2018-03-8</date> CO Add first use cases, add findings of the WG1 meeting in Prague:
    refine selection criteria and balancing criteria</change>
   <change><date>2018-09-05</date>CO divided the document into two documents: one for sampling
    criteria, one for discussion about canonicity and corpus design.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>
  <!-- <head>Sampling criteria for the ELTeC</head>
   <div>
    <head>Outline</head>
    <list type="ordered">
     <item>Task</item>
     <item>Method</item>
     <item>Objectives of sampling criteria</item>
     <item>Sampling criteria</item>
     <item>Metadata for texts in ELTeC</item>
     <item>Literature</item>
    </list>
   </div>-->
   <div>
    <head>Task</head>
    <p>The task for WG1 is to develop guidelines for data and metadata for the creation of the
     ELTeC. This task can be split up into several distinct tasks: Guidelines for corpus design,
     basic annotation and metadata schemes and workflow. This discussion paper focuses on corpus
     design and metadata because both tasks interplay with each other.</p>
    <p>The goal of CA16204 is to create a big benchmark corpus of literature from 1840-1920 (first
     period) for different computational distant reading methods for corpus annotation and analysis.
     The task of creating annotation guidelines of WG1 needs to be closely communicated and
     coordinated with WG2 in order to know which methods and tools needs which kind(s) of annotation
     model and format. The same holds for the development of the metadata scheme. </p>
    <p>For creating such a benchmark corpus, we need a corpus design which allows for a
     comparability of texts and individual sub-collections according to different metadata set(s).
     It should be possible for every COST Action member to sample sub-collections from the ELTeC for
     specific tasks and research questions. In a first step, we focus on the development of clear,
     operationalized, transparent and motivated selection criteria for the corpus.</p>
    <p>It is important to stress that we do not intend to define what a novel is by defining what
     kind of selection criteria we will use for ELTeC. The category novel may be divided into three
     groups where at least one of the following core criteria is met: a) textual: length (>10.000
     words), prose, fiction, narrative structure b) peritextual (the term ‘novel’ (or its
     equivalent) in the title or subtitle of the text ) and c) contextual: the text is
     bibliographically listed with the UDC: 82-31 Novels. Full-length stories.</p>
   </div>
   <div>
    <head>Method</head>
    <p>We follow a non-normative but metadata-based approach of sampling criteria which will follow
     a corpus design approach. Corpus sampling criteria are mostly oriented/developed by the
     research question or/and contexts of the corpus creators group. In CA16204, we have neither
     only a single research question nor a fixed and previously known corpus creator group. The
     research context of the Action is more interested in knowledge production in a methodological
     sense and does not prefer a single method, model or theory. Furthermore, the member group of
     the Action will fluctuate and consist of researches from different disciplines with different
     theoretical and cultural contexts. Thus, we need to build the corpus design on a methodical
     basis. With this method, we will also be able to select canonical texts as well but not
     exclusively. </p>
    <p> Representativeness is a kind of ideal which we would like to pursue but which cannot be
     achieved as whole. We will therefore aim to represent the variety of a population. In line with
     the MoU, the ELTeC will be designed as a monitor corpus where texts (from different languages
     and periods) can be added over time. We then need to decide which criterion is balanced in
     which way and interplays with other criteria.</p>
   </div>
   <div>
    <head>Objectives of sampling criteria </head>
    <p>According to the MoU, the corpus design should be balanced with respect to language and
     publication date of the texts. This means that the corpus should not be based solely on
     chronological criteria, meaning that we need a text from each year of the period in question.
     The main sampling criterion ‘language’ will require not to include translations at all. We will
     prefer to take the first edition of a novel or editions of these novels. By a novel, we prefer
     to take the edition of the book, hence we don't prefer novels only printed in journals, unless
     a particular literary tradition only features novels printed in serial format. If we consider
     editions of a novel, these editions should be freely available (free licences for reusing them.
     The first edition is more interesting from a philological point of view. It represents the
     authentic texts of the authors. Dealing with historical texts might require some cleaning up or
     normalizations. We will merge all word forms which are seperated by line breaks. At the moment,
     we must assume that there are no (sufficiently good) normalization tools for every language.
     Later editions of a novel may be already normalized in some way. This might lead to different
     text representations in ELTeC which should be indicated in the metadata. </p>
    <p>Considering also later freely available editions of a novel has two advantages: First,
     members of the Action already can provide machine-readable text documents (html, TEI etc.) of
     later editions and second, in some languages it might be easier to find later editions which
     already exist in a machine-readable format (in this way we do not have to put effort in
     digitizing them).</p>
    <p> Electronically availability should not be a leading sampling criterion althoug availability
     is a limiting factor. A text should not be excluded from ELTeC because it is not digitized, but
     it should be excluded if the text cannot be made freely available in ELTeC. If we only use
     availability as a selecting criterion, we are at risk of copying projects such as ‘Gutenberg’
     for example. The issue remains of finding additional funds to digitise non-canonical books. Un
     til that moment, the solution would be to create pilot corpora (that can later be supplemented
     or substituted by an alterna tive) for literatures that do not have a significant number of
     digitized texts. </p>
    <p> We then need additional criteria which can be applied without having to know (read) the
     texts in question. The criteria should be checked without a deep knowledge about the texts.
     Otherwise, this will oppose the goal of the whole Action and the methodical approach of distant
     reading. The criteria should be operationalizable, meaning decidable from text metadata. Here,
     we define text metadata in a wider scope than only the classical bibliographical metadata. In
     this way corpus design interacts with metadata. Some of the text’s metadata can be used as
     sampling criteria. These criteria are text-external and -internal criteria (cf. Hunston 2008)
     on which we then need to rely. The selection criteria may be assisted by bibliographical
     overviews (wherever available) for each language in order to avoid possible canon-derived bias. </p>
    <p>We suggest using an online table as a means of collecting nominations for inclusion in the
     ELTeC but other methods are feasible. </p>
   </div>
   <div>
    <head> Sampling criteria </head>
    <p>For creating a language collection two steps have to be done: First step is selection:
     identifying text candidates. Second step is balancing: proportion within the corpus. Both steps
     are defined in this document.</p>
    <p>The following principles apply: </p>
    <list type="unordered">
     <item>We will represent the variety of production and aim to maximize the variety within each
      time period.</item>
     <item>We will prefer to collect novels published as a book in first as well as later editions
      over novels published in serial publications (journals).</item>
     <item>We will not include translations.</item>
     <item>We will consider only freely available texts and trying to reuse already digitized
      texts.</item>
     <item>We will use non-normative sampling criteria which allow for selecting canonical novels
      and non-canonical novels.</item>
     <item>Metadata should indicate the type of text representation (normalized or non-normalized,
      first or later editions etc.). </item>
     <item>We will strictly follow the selection and balancing criteria and we prefer 80 novels
      meeting these criteria over 100 novels which do not meet the criteria.</item>
    </list>
   <!-- <p>Organization</p>
    <list>
     <item>Please note: Contact the sampling support Team: Carolin, Lou, Pieter and Diana! Task: To
      control the corpus sampling according to the selection criteria. </item>
    </list>-->
   <div> <head>Eligibility criteria </head>
    <p> In order to be considered for inclusion, a text must... </p>
    <list>
     <item>have been first published as a book (or exceptionally as a serial publication) between
      1840 and 1920s, </item>
     <item>have first been published in a European country. [maybe not "first": within that
      decade],</item>
     <item>be a novel, i.e. a fictional prose narrative of at least 10000 words</item>
     <item>have originally been written in the language of the given subcollection.</item>
    </list>
   
     <p>The MoU defines the languages to be sampled. It does not propose distinguishing regional
      variation (e.g. in German), nor geographical variation (e.g. the French spoken in Belgium,
      France, or Switzerland). It assumes only European varieties, so English excludes US English;
      French excludes Quebecois. </p>
     <p> We follow a language-based approach (not country-based). This means for example that we
      include Swiss German texts in the German language collection. We prefer standard varieties
      over dialect varieties if sampling criteria for text candidates are met. </p>
     <list>
      <item>Open Question: Maybe some Exceptions: - Publication place is a sometimes a problem:
       e.g. for Portuguese novels published in as Brazilian publications or Croatian authors
       published in Germany. </item>
      <item>Possible Languages for the first iteration: Dutch, English, French, German, Greek,
       Italian, Polish, Portuguese, Russian, Spanish, Hungarian.</item>
     </list></div>
    <div><head>Composition criteria </head>
    <p>This section briefly summarizes the classification criteria applied, and also the
    ideal target proportions of titles to be included for each category within the balanced collection. </p>
    <list type="gloss">

     <label> Date : 1840 to 1920 (first iteration)</label>
     <item>
      <p>We will divide into four groups</p>
      <list type="unordered">
       <item>group A (1840-1859): code T1</item>
       <item>group B (1860-1879): code T2</item>
       <item>group C (1880-1899): code T3</item>
       <item>group D (1900-1920): code T4</item>
      </list>
      <p>At least 20% of the titles should be associated with each defined time slot.</p>
     </item>
     <label>Reprint count</label>
     <item>
      <p>We propose to use the number of times a work has been reprinted during a specific period
       as an objective measure of its
       reception. We count the number of reprints attested during the period 1970-2010 according to Worldcat or a relevant national library catalogue and classify texts as either: </p><list>
       <item>low: less than 2 reprints</item>
        <item>high: more than 2 reprints</item>
       </list>
       <p>Note that we do not include digitizations of texts in the reprint count.</p>
   <p>At least 30% of titles should be classified as "high"; at least 30% should be classified as "low".
    </p>
  </item>
     <label>Author gender</label>
     <item>
      <p>We use the following three categories for actual (not claimed) author gender </p><list>
       <item>male</item>
       <item>female</item>
       <item>mixed (undefined or more than one author)</item>
      </list>
      <p>At least 10% and at most 50% of the titles have a female author.</p>
     </item>
     <label>Author title count</label>
     <item><p>The number of titles per author should be controlled. Ideally, no author should be represented by more than three titles. We count
     <list><item>the number of authors represented by a single title</item><item>the number of authors represented by exactly three novels</item></list></p>
      <p>9 to 11 authors are represented by exactly three novels; all other authors are represented by a single title only</p></item>
     <label>Length</label>
     <item>
      <p>We classify titles by their length as follows:</p>
      <list>
       <item>short (10k-50k word tokens) </item>
       <item>medium (50k-100k word tokens)</item>
       <item>long (>100k word tokens)</item>
      </list>
      <p>At least 20% of titles should be short; at least 20% should be long. </p>
     </item>

     <label>Kind of novel</label>
     <item>
      <p>It is an open issue how to classify novels by topic. We are not sure how to use this as a
       sampling criterion. Instead we will add metadata about the subgenre.</p>
     </item>
     <label>Example</label>
     <item>
      <p>The following table suggests minimum and maximum numbers of titles to be selected for each
       criterion. For each language collection we collect 100 different novels. In each date group,
       we will have 25 novels. In a language collection, we will have at least 30 novels for the
       category high reprints and 30 for the category low reprints. In a language collection, we
       will have at least 10 novels from female authors and 20 novels per length category (long,
       medium short). </p>
      <table rend="rules">
       <row role="label">
        <cell>Language</cell>
        <cell>Date Group</cell>
        <cell>Reprint Category</cell>
        <cell>Author Category</cell>
        <cell>Length Category</cell>
       </row>
       <row>
        <cell>100</cell>
        <cell>25</cell>
        <cell>30</cell>
        <cell>10</cell>
        <cell>20</cell>
       </row>
      </table>
     </item>
    </list></div>
   </div>

   <div>
    <head> Metadata for texts in ELTeC </head>
    <p>We list here some examples of the metadata items to be collected for each text. These will be provided by
     specific components of the TEI Header structure. </p>
    <p>See <ref target="https://distantreading.github.io/Schema/eltec-1.html">Encoding Guidelines</ref> for more details.</p>
    <list type="unordered">
     <item>title</item>
     <item>subtitle</item>
     <item>publication date</item>
     <item>publication place</item>
     <item>publisher</item>
     <item>series</item>
     <item>editor</item>
     <item>author<list type="unordered">
       <item>name</item>
       <item>sex</item>
       <item>first language</item>
       <item>place of birth</item>
       <item>entry of a person database such as GND or VIAF if available</item>
      </list></item>
     <item>size<list type="unordered">
       <item>in words / in tokens</item>
      </list></item>
     <item>pages</item>
     <item>topics (cf. Falkentheorie)<list type="unordered">
       <item>politics, crime, espionage, provincial, school, adventure, war, faith, domestic,
        nature, factory, love, family, history, mystery, urban life, art, rural life</item>
      </list></item>
     <item>subgenre<list type="unordered">
       <item>work-in-progress novel</item>
      </list></item>
     <item>Narrator(s)<list type="unordered">
       <item>first person</item>
       <item>third person</item>
       <item>authorial/omniscient narrator</item>
      </list></item>
     <item>canonicity/reception<list type="unordered">
       <item>rated by a canon: y/n</item>
       <item>canon</item>
      </list></item>
     <item>keywords<list type="unordered">
       <item>from OPACs? others? Own?</item>
      </list></item>
     <item>language<list type="unordered">
       <item>possible: language area, language type (e.g. German, Bavarian)</item>
      </list></item>
     <item>Source reference (if available)<list type="unordered">
       <item>e.g. DTA, textgrid etc.</item>
      </list></item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div>
    <head>Literature</head>
    <listBibl>
     <bibl>Algee-Hewitt, Mark; McGurl, Mark (2015): <title>Between Canon and Corpus. Six
       Perspectives on the 20th-Century Novels.</title> Stanford Literary Lab Pamphlet no 8. </bibl>
     <bibl>Biber, Douglas (1993): <title level="a">Representativeness in Corpus Design.</title> In:
       <title level="j">Literary and Linguistic Computing </title>(8), 243–257.</bibl>
     <bibl>Herrmann, Leonhard (2011): <title level="a">System? Kanon? Epoche?</title> In: Matthias
      Beilein, Claudia Stockinger und Simone Winko (Hg.): <title>Kanon, Wertung und Vermittlung.
       Literatur in der Wissensgesellschaft.</title> Berlin: De Gruyter (Studien und Texte zur
      Sozialgeschichte der Literatur, Bd. 129), S. 59–75.</bibl>
     <bibl>Hunston, Susan (2008): <title level="a">Collection strategies and design
       decisions.</title> In: Anke Lüdeling und Merja Kytö (Hg.): <title>Corpus Linguistics. An
       International Handbook</title>. 2 Bände. Berlin: De Gruyter (1), S. 154–168.</bibl>
     <bibl>IFLA (2009): <title>Functional Requirements for Bibliographic Records</title> (Technical
      Report). Online verfügbar unter
      http://www.ifla.org/publications/functional-requirements-for-bibliographic-records, zuletzt
      geprüft am 23.12.2016.</bibl>
     <bibl>Lüdeling, Anke (2011): <title level="a">Corpora in Linguistics. Sampling and
       Annotation</title>. In: Karl Grandin (Hg.): <title level="m">Going Digital. Evolutionary and
       Revolutionary Aspects of Digitization</title>. New York: Science History Publications (Nobel
      Symposium, 147), 220–243.</bibl>
     <bibl>Moisl, Hermann (2009): <title level="a">Exploratory Multivariate Analysis</title>. In:
      Anke Lüdeling und Merja Kytö (Hg.): <title>Corpus Linguistics. An International
       Handbook</title>. 2 Bände. Berlin: De Gruyter (2), S. 874–899.</bibl>
     <bibl>Winko, Simone (1996): <title level="a">Literarische Wertung und Kanonbildung</title>. In:
       <title level="m">Grundzüge der Literaturwissenschaft.</title> Hrsg. v. H. L. Arnold und H.
      Detering. München, 585–600.</bibl>
     <bibl>van Zundert, Joris; Andrews, Tara L. (2017): <title level="a">Qu'est-ce qu'un texte
       numérique? A new rationale for the digital representation of text.</title> In: <title
       level="j">Digital Scholarship in the Humanities </title>(32), S. 78–88. DOI:
      10.1093/llc/fqx039.</bibl>
    </listBibl>
   </div>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
