<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Sampling criteria for the ELTeC</title>
                <author>Cost Action CA16204 – WG1 </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>2018-01</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Unpublished discussion document prepared for COST Action 16204</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
                <change><date>2018-01-30</date> LB revised table; added some discussion to criteria;
                    tarted up bibliog </change>
                <change><date>2018-01-27</date> LB converted to XML</change>
                <change><date>2018-01-27</date> CO Final draft</change>
                <change><date>2018-03-8</date> CO Add first use cases, add findings of the WG1
                    meeting in Prague: refine selection criteria and balancing criteria</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <head>Sampling criteria for the ELTeC</head>
            <div>
                <head>Outline</head>
                <list type="ordered">
                    <item>Task</item>
                    <item>Method</item>
                    <item>Representativeness</item>
                    <item>Requirements of sampling criteria</item>
                    <item>Sampling criteria</item>
                    <item>Metadata for texts in ELTeC</item>
                    <item>First use cases (WG 1 meeting Prague)</item>
                    <item>Literature</item>
                </list>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Task</head>
                <p>The task for WG1 is to develop guidelines for data and metadata for the creation
                    of the ELTeC. This task can be split up into several distinct tasks: Guidelines
                    for corpus design, basic annotation and metadata schemes and workflow. This
                    discussion paper focuses on corpus design and metadata because both tasks
                    interplay with each other.</p>
                <p>The goal of CA16204 is to create a big benchmark corpus of literature from
                    1850-1920 (first period) for different computational distant reading methods for
                    corpus annotation and analysis. The task of creating annotation guidelines of
                    WG1 needs to be closely communicated and coordinated with WG2 in order to know
                    which methods and tools needs which kind(s) of annotation model and format. The
                    same holds for the development of the metadata scheme. </p>
                <p>For creating such a benchmark corpus, we need a corpus design which allows for a
                    comparability of texts and individual sub-collections according to different
                    metadata set(s). It should be possible for every COST Action member to sample
                    sub-collections from the ELTeC for specific tasks and research questions. In a
                    first step, we focus on the development of clear, operationalized, transparent
                    and motivated selection criteria for the corpus.</p>
                <p>It is important to stress that we do not intend to define what a novel is by
                    defining what kind of selection criteria we will use for ELTeC.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Method</head>
                <p>First, we would like to discuss whether the task of corpus building requires
                    normative selection criteria (canon) or methodical selection criteria (corpus
                    sampling). The first and foremost important difference between the approaches is
                    the motivation of criteria. A canon is the portrait of someone’s prestigious
                    social, cultural, economic status and it reflects normative self-promotional
                    legitimating and rating decisions. In contrast, corpus design follows a research
                    question or context and is therefore more research goal oriented. A second
                    important aspect is the way of considering the actual texts. As Moisl (2009:
                    876) puts it ‘Data is ontologically different from the world.’ So there is a
                    difference between texts in the world and data we create. By texts, we may
                    consider the manifestation or the extension or the work of a text (cf. IFLA
                    2009). A canon can contain an extension of a certain text which is available in
                    different languages and prints. Ontologically, these different levels of text
                    are different from what a text in a corpus might be (cf. van Zundert and Andrews
                    2017). This means, that digitization is a kind of annotation, hence
                    interpretation (Odebrecht et al 2017). A representation of a text in a corpus
                    (e.g. transcription, OCR) is the result of interpretation. A corpus design needs
                    to consider this for sampling and digitization issues. </p>
                <p>At the end of the Action, ELTeC should contain literary texts (novels) from a
                    distinct period and in several languages. For each language (and thus for each
                    cultural context) there exists a diversity of canons which reflect different
                    prestigious groups such as publishers, authors and readers. These actors and
                    their possible influence on canon building is multi-relational. Each canon is a
                    result of rating texts from different perspectives. The assessment can reflect
                    intellectual rating (a text is a representative of a certain literature period,
                    is influential, is important), economical rating (a text is published in more
                    than one print run), or readers rating (a text is most popular within a certain
                    reader group) (cf. Hermann 2011 or Winko 1996). All these ratings can change
                    over time and may also interplay which each other. A canon can therefore reflect
                    different interpretation of ‘famous’, ‘important’ or ‘influential’ texts. These
                    criteria are not overall comparable. For example, texts from a smaller language
                    community such as Czech are less likely to be frequently reprinted than English
                    texts of the same period and genre. Additionally, the awareness level of texts
                    depends on the influence of the country and their publishing houses.</p>
                <p>The criteria derived from a canon are not completely comparable and categorical.
                    Which prestigious group’s canon should be considered, which should be excluded,
                    and why? Are there comparable canons for novels in all countries of the language
                    in question? Algee-Hewitt and McGurl (2015) show an approach to corpus design
                    based on several canons and which kind of problems occur. Each analysis of the
                    corpus than only shows the different effects of the decisions made by the
                    normative group. Considering national canons is also very difficult and somewhat
                    problematic. An example is the German National Canon of literature which was
                    developed in the 18th century and was promoted by the national educational
                    system until the 1990. Since German reunification, the educational system has
                    not promoted a strict canon and does not recommend a list of books to be read in
                    school or at university (cf. Winko 1996). Thus, taking such types of canons as
                    part of a sampling base of ELTeC would mean reflecting a political and social
                    past of German education and politics. Choosing between canons can then mean
                    choosing between tastes of (current) literature (in past and present) and tastes
                    of past literature when the canon builder rates historical texts. Finally, these
                    canons are not built to be the sampling guidelines for a corpus which we would
                    like to build in the Action.</p>
                <p>The MoU of CA16204 formulates the goal as follows: “The main aim and objective of
                    the Action is to This Action will develop the resources and methods necessary to
                    change the way European literary history is written.” This goal requires a new
                    approach to corpus design, metadata design and annotation models. As Fowler
                    (2002, 214) puts it: ‘The current canon sets limits to our understanding of
                    literature, in several ways’. Relying on canons will obstruct the Action’s goal
                    in a fundamental way. Canons provide traditional and normative access to the
                    history of literature. In contrast, the Action focuses on new approaches to tell
                    another story. Instead, we might decide that our collection should contain a
                    mixture of works that have never been reprinted since their first appearance,
                    works that have been reprinted a small number of times within one or two decades
                    of their first appearance, and works that have been reprinted in almost every
                    decade since their first appearance. </p>
                <p>Therefore, we argue for a non-normative but metadata-based approach of sampling
                    criteria which will follow a corpus design approach. Corpus sampling criteria
                    are mostly oriented/developed by the research question or/and contexts of the
                    corpus creators group. In CA16204, we have neither a distinct research question
                    nor a fixed and previously known corpus creator group. The research context of
                    the Action is more interested in knowledge production in a methodological sense
                    and does not prefer a single method, model or theory. Furthermore, the member
                    group of the Action will fluctuate and consist of researches from different
                    disciplines with different theoretical and cultural contexts. Thus, we need to
                    build the corpus design on a methodical basis. With this method, we will also be
                    able to select canonical texts as well but not exclusively. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Representativeness and balance</head>
                <p>Additional to the aspect of ‘prestige’ (canon), the aspect of representativeness
                    is problematic for corpus design. Developing criteria for corpus design means to
                    decide which kind of sample of the world shall be included in the data base.
                    Obviously, including the whole population of 9th century literature in several
                    languages is impossible. So we need to make a compromise between what we would
                    like to have in the corpus (all literature) and what we can put in the corpus
                    (sample). </p>
                <p>It is a truism that there is no such thing as a ‘good’ or a ‘bad’ corpus, because
                    how a corpus is designed depends on what kind of corpus it is and how it is
                    going to be used. (Hunston 2008, 155)</p>
                <p>Following Hunston (2008), a corpus design needs to follow the research goal. For
                    the Action, representativeness may be the relationship between the corpus and
                    the body of literature in question. ‘Representativeness refers to the extent to
                    which a sample includes the full range of variability in a population’ (Biber
                    1993, 243). To say something about the representativeness of a corpus requires
                    knowledge about the whole population of literature (in the period in question).
                    Actually, we don’t know every book of every language published/read/discussed in
                    Europe in the period in question. It is further ‘impossible to identify a
                    complete list of ‘categories’ that would exhaustively account for all texts
                    produced in a given language’, (Hunston 2008, 161) or context. Such categories
                    can refer to various factors such as characteristics of authors, e.g., gender or
                    place of birth, publishers, topics of the texts, readership etc. Against the
                    background of canon building, there is also ‘no true measure of the
                    ‘significance’ of a type of discourse to a community’. The chance, that a corpus
                    represents the whole population of something increases with the size of a
                    corpus. In this way, size and representativeness are connected. <note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="1"><p rend="footnote text"> See Biber (1993)
                            and Hunston (2008) for a detailed discussion.</p></note>
                    Representativeness is therefore a kind of ideal which we would like to pursue
                    but which cannot be achieved as whole. In line with the MoU, the ELTeC can be
                    designed as a monitor corpus where texts (from different languages and periods)
                    can be added over time. </p>
                <p>Balance refers to the internal proportion of the corpus. Note that a fully
                    balanced corpus is an ideal which we only can try to achieve next to the ideal
                    of representativeness (Hunston 2008, 163). According the MoU, the corpus shall
                    contain 2,500 full-texts novels at least in 10 different languages:</p>
                <list type="unordered">
                    <item>Languages: Dutch, English, French, German, Greek, Italian, Polish,
                        Portuguese, Russian, Spanish (ELTeC core)</item>
                    <item>first iteration: 6 subcollections (100 novels per language) 1850 to 1920
                        starting with British, French, Spanish, German, Greek, Polish</item>
                    <item>second iteration: 4 subcollections (100 novels per language) 1850 to
                        1920</item>
                    <item>third iteration: 6 subcollections in additional languages and
                        subcollections for all 16 languages 1780-1850, </item>
                    <item>We will also try to include additional languages such as Hungarian,
                        Serbian, Swiss , Romanian, Czech, Latvian, Norwegian.</item>
                </list>
                <p>In this way, ELTeC is balanced with respect to language. With respect to genre,
                    the corpus is not balanced but homogenous; all texts in the corpus shall be full
                    novels. With respect to time, the corpus design shall focus on the period 1850
                    to 1920.</p>
                <p>Before discussing the criteria in more detail, we would like to ask another
                    methodical question concerning corpus sampling: would we like to use each
                    criterion, with the intention to represent the variety of possible values, or
                    should the sample represent the distribution of those values across the
                    population? </p>
                <p>Let’s say we wish to select 100 texts from a population of texts published over a
                    period of (say) 20 decades. We might select five texts from the first decade,
                    five from the second, and so on, making up our 100 titles, evenly spread across
                    the possible decades. The probability that a text in our corpus will come from
                    any given decade will always be the same: 1 in 5. This selection represents the
                        <emph>variety</emph> of possible values for the criterion. Suppose now that
                    we look more closely at the number of titles from each decade actually available
                    in the population we are sampling. It’s more than likely that this number will
                    vary significantly: for example, we might notice that there are 2000 titles
                    published in decade x, and only 100 in decade y. To represent this population
                        <emph>statistically </emph>we should therefore make it 20 times more
                    probable that a randomly chosen title will come from decade x than from decade
                    y. Since the total number of titles we can choose is quite small relative to the
                    total number available in the population, strict application of this principle
                    may mean that we cannot choose any titles at all from some decades. This is one
                    reason for preferring to make our sampling represent variety rather than
                    frequency; another is that we cannot choose fractional numbers of titles. When
                    we start considering more than one criterion, the task of ensuring that the
                    numbers in our sample accurately reflect the distribution of all values across
                    the population becomes prohibitively complex. </p>
                <p>Following the approach of representing the variety of a population, we then need
                    to decide which criterion is balanced in which way and interplays with other
                    criteria. For example, we may want to choose novels from male and female authors
                    in a balanced way. This may mean that in the total of all novels one half will
                    be from female authors. Without any further regulation, we might have more
                    female authors in one decade than in other decades. If we would like to have an
                    equal number of male and female authors in every decade, we need to link the
                    criterion of the author’s gender with the criterion of time. Doing this, might
                    complicate the selection process (cf. finding novels for this proportion in
                    every decade of the period in question). So we have to decide which categories
                    shall be present in a balanced way in the corpus. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Requirements of sampling criteria</head>
                <p>According to the MoU, the corpus design should be balanced with respect to
                    language and publication date of the texts. This means that the corpus should
                    not be based solely on chronological criteria, meaning that we need a text from
                    each year of the period in question. The main sampling criterion ‘language’ will
                    require not to include translations at all. We will take the first edition of a
                    novel or editions of these novels. By a novel, we mean the edition of the book,
                    hence excluding novels only printed in journals. If we consider editions of a
                    novel, these editions should be freely available (free licences for reusing
                    them. The first edition is more interesting from a philological point of view.
                    It represents the authentic texts of the authors. Dealing with historical texts
                    might require some cleaning up or normalizations. We will merge all word forms
                    which are seperated by line breaks. At the moment, we must assume that there are
                    no (sufficiently good) normalization tools for every language. Later editions of
                    a novel may be already normalized in some way. This might lead to different text
                    representations in ELTeC which should be indicated in the metadata. </p>
                <p>Considering also later freely available editions of a novel has two advantages:
                    First, members of the Action already can provide machine-readable text documents
                    (html, TEI etc.) of later editions and second, in some languages it might be
                    easier to find later editions which already exist in a machine-readable format
                    (in this way we do not have to put effort in digitizing them).</p>
                <p> Electronically availability should not be a leading sampling criterion althoug
                    availability is a limiting factor. A text should not be excluded from ELTeC
                    because it is not digitized, but it should be excluded if the text cannot be
                    made freely available in ELTeC. If we only use availability as a selecting
                    criterion, we are at risk of copying projects such as ‘Gutenberg’ for example.
                    We then need additional criteria which can be applied without having to know
                    (read) the texts in question. The criteria should be checked without a deep
                    knowledge about the texts. Otherwise, this will oppose the goal of the whole
                    Action and the methodical approach of distant reading. The criteria should be
                    operationalizable, meaning decidable from text metadata. Here, we define text
                    metadata in a wider scope than only the classical bibliographical metadata. In
                    this way corpus design interacts with metadata. Some of the text’s metadata can
                    be used a sampling criteria. These criteria are text-external and -internal
                    criteria (cf. Hunston 2008) on which we then need to rely. </p>
                <p>We suggest using an online table as a means of collecting nominations for
                    inclusion in the ELTeC but other methods are feasible. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head> Sampling criteria </head>
                <p>Principles:</p>
                <list type="unordered">
                    <item>We will represent the variation of production and aim to maximize the
                        variety within each time period.</item>
                    <item>We will consider novels published as a book in first as well as later
                        editions.</item>
                    <item>We will not include translations.</item>
                    <item>We will consider only freely available texts and trying to reuse already
                        digitized texts.</item>
                    <item>We will use non-normative sampling criteria which allow for selecting
                        canonical novels and non-canonical novels.</item>
                    <item>Metadata should indicate the type of text representation (normalized or
                        non-normalized, first or later editions etc.). </item>
                    <item>Open Question: do we allow for normalization, if available? (WG2)</item>
                </list>
                <p>Organization</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Please note: Contact the sampling support Team: Carolin, Pieter and Diana!
                        Task: To control the corpus sampling according to the selection criteria. </item>
                    <item> List of documents in ELTeC core:
                        https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1LHRWEJdi8lPPvVKjjNdS3Tv1_vd0sP0_3GvoGw2c23w/edit?ts=5a6a36f2#gid=698963499</item>
                </list>
                <p>Criteria: Eligibility. </p>
                <p> In order to be included, a text must... </p>
                <list>
                    <item>have been first published as a book between 1850 and 1920, sub-grouped and
                        equally split by decades. </item>
                    <item>have first been published in a European country. [maybe not "first":
                        within that decade]</item>
                    <item>be a novel, i.e. a fictional prose narrative.</item>
                    <item>have originally been written in the language of the given
                        subcollection</item>
                </list>
                <p>Criteria: Composition. </p>
                <p>Among the novels in each language the subcollection must contain... </p>
                <list>
                    <item>at least 10%-50% have been written by female authors for the language
                        subcollection.</item>
                    <item>at least 10 authors are represented with three novels.</item>
                    <item>at least 30% are highly canonized novels, at least 30% should be
                        non-canonized novels, based on reprints two groups: 1 Group: canon.
                        reprinted more than once 2. Group: non-canon. not or once reprinted, period:
                        1980-2000</item>
                    <item>at least 20% are short novels (10-50k word tokens), at least 20% are long
                        novels (>200k word tokens).</item>
                </list>
                <list type="gloss">

                    <label> Date : 1850 to 1920 (first iteration)</label>
                    <item>
                        <p>We will divide by decade</p>
                        <list type="unordered">
                            <item>group A(1850-1860)</item>
                            <item>group B (1861-1870)</item>
                            <item>group C (1871-1880)</item>
                            <item>group D (1881-1890) </item>
                            <item>group E (1891-1900)</item>
                            <item>group F (1901-1910)</item>
                            <item>group G (1911-1920)</item>
                            <item>Open Question: Should we extend the period to 1840?</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>

                    <label>Language of the text</label>
                    <item><p>The MoA defines the languages to be sampled. It does not propose
                            distinguishing regional variation (e.g. in German), nor geographical
                            variation (e.g. the French of Belgium or France or Switzerland). It
                            assumes only European varieties, so English excludes US English; French
                            excludes Quebecois. </p><list>
                            <item>Open Question: Maybe some Exceptions: - Publication place is a
                                sometimes a problem: e.g. for Portuguese Novels published in as
                                Brazilian publications or Croatian authors published in Germany. </item>
                            <item>Possible Languages for the first iteration: Dutch, English,
                                French, German, Greek, Italian, Polish, Portuguese, Russian,
                                Spanish, Hungarian</item>
                        </list></item>
                    <label>Reprint count</label>
                    <item><p>We propose to use the number of times a work is reprinted as an
                            objective measure of its reception, using categories like the following: </p><list>
                                <item>low: no reprints at all, or one reprint (30% of all novels in a language collection)</item>
                            <item>high: reprinted more than once (30% of all novels in a language collection)</item> 
                                <item>We will not include digitizations of texts in the reprint count.</item>
                        </list></item>
                    <label>Author gender</label>
                    <item>
                        <p>We use the following three categories for actual (not claimed) author
                            gender </p><list>
                            <item>male</item>
                            <item>female</item>
                            <item>mixed (undefined or more than one author)</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <label>Length</label>
                    <item>
                        <p>We should try to include a variety of lengths</p>
                        <list>
                            <item>short (10-50k word tokens) </item>
                            <item>medium (50k-200k word tokens)</item>
                            <item>long (>200k word tokens)</item>
                        </list></item>

                    <label>Kind of novel</label>
                    <item>
                        <p>It is an open issue how to classify novels by topic. We are not sure how
                            to use this as a sampling criterion. </p>
                        <list>
                            <item>Main theme </item>
                        </list></item>
                </list>
                <p>The following table suggests minimum and maximum numbers of titles to be selected
                    for each criterion. For example, for each language, we would aim to select
                    100 different titles. Of these, no more than 20 will come from
                    each date period defined above. Of these, we will aim to have between 5 and 10
                    examples from each of the reprint categories defined (high, medium, low). Of
                    these, the number produced by male authors will be between 5 and 8, as will the
                    number produced by female authors, and the number produced by authors of unknown
                    or indeterminate sex. </p>
                <table rend="rules">
                    <row role="label">
                        <cell>Language</cell>
                        <cell>Date</cell>
                        <cell>Reprint</cell>
                        <cell>Author</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>100</cell>
                        <cell>20</cell>
                        <cell>5-10</cell>
                        <cell>5-8</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>

            </div>
            <div>
                <head> Metadata for texts in ELTeC </head>
                <p>We list here the metadata items to be collected for each text. These will be
                    provided by specific components of the TEI Header structure, as definding in WG
                    paper on Encoding.</p>
                <p>See Encoding Proposal for more details.</p>
                <list type="unordered">
                    <item>title</item>
                    <item>subtitle</item>
                    <item>publication date</item>
                    <item>publication place</item>
                    <item>publisher</item>
                    <item>series</item>
                    <item>editor</item>
                    <item>author<list type="unordered">
                            <item>name</item>
                            <item>sex</item>
                            <item>first language</item>
                            <item>place of birth</item>
                            <item>entry of a person database such as GND if available</item>
                        </list></item>
                    <item>size<list type="unordered">
                            <item>in words / in tokens</item>
                        </list></item>
                    <item>pages</item>
                    <item>topics (cf. Falkentheorie)<list type="unordered">
                            <item>politics, crime, espionage, provincial, school, adventure, war,
                                faith, domestic, nature, factory </item>
                        </list></item>
                    <item>subgenre<list type="unordered">
                            <item>work-in-progress novel</item>
                        </list></item>
                    <item>Narrator<list type="unordered">
                            <item>first person</item>
                            <item>third person</item>
                            <item>authorial narrator</item>
                        </list></item>
                    <item>canonicity/reception<list type="unordered">
                            <item>rated by a canon: y/n</item>
                            <item>canon</item>
                        </list></item>
                    <item>keywords<list type="unordered">
                            <item>from OPACs? others? Own?</item>
                        </list></item>
                    <item>language<list type="unordered">
                            <item>possible: language area, language type (e.g. German,
                                Bavarian)</item>
                        </list></item>
                    <item>Source reference (if available)<list type="unordered">
                            <item>e.g. DTA, textgrid etc.</item>
                        </list></item>
                </list>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>6. First use cases (WG 1)</head>
                <list>
                    <item>DS: intertextuality : how literary works are mentioned </item>
                    <item>FJ: character constellations : network measures </item>
                    <item>CS: MoU says "authorship attribution, topic modelling, character network
                        analysis, stylistic analysis" </item>
                    <item>DS: What kinds of places/names of places are described in different
                        novels</item>
                    <item>LB: structural properties, formal organization</item>
                    <item>DS: description of characters; types of characters; readers as
                        characters</item>
                    <item>JR: do stylometric authorship attribution methods work in all languages in
                        same way</item>
                    <item>?: what do people eat</item>
                    <item>B: location, places where stories take part. morpho-syntax, readability;
                        e.g. words/sentence</item>
                    <item>BN: how about metaphors</item>
                    <item>FJ: narratalogical features direct speech</item>
                    <item>DS: presentation of other European cultures</item>
                    <item>BN: sentiment analysis</item>
                    <item>LB: bibliometric aspects: book history</item>
                    <item>CO: diachronic development; publication place; gender</item>
                    <item>DS: addressing forms</item>
                    <item>G: Evolution and validation of literary movements; empirical
                        definition</item>
                    <item>BN: temporal expressions</item>
                    <item>FJ: all of the above in a comparative perspective varying by e.g.
                        male/female, date, place</item>
                    <item>CS: subgenres?</item>
                    <item>P: Rate and measurability of change; how innovation spreads; both in topic
                        and mode of expression </item>
                    <item>JS: Character idiolects ; places</item>
                    <item>evolution of wordsenses over time</item>
                    <item>local coherence; cohesiveness; evolution of realism into modernism</item>
                </list>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Literature</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Algee-Hewitt, Mark; McGurl, Mark (2015): <title>Between Canon and Corpus.
                            Six Perspectives on the 20th-Century Novels.</title> Stanford Literary
                        Lab Pamphlet no 8. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Biber, Douglas (1993): <title level="a">Representativeness in Corpus
                            Design.</title> In: <title level="j">Literary and Linguistic Computing
                        </title>(8), 243–257.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Herrmann, Leonhard (2011): <title level="a">System? Kanon? Epoche?</title>
                        In: Matthias Beilein, Claudia Stockinger und Simone Winko (Hg.):
                            <title>Kanon, Wertung und Vermittlung. Literatur in der
                            Wissensgesellschaft.</title> Berlin: De Gruyter (Studien und Texte zur
                        Sozialgeschichte der Literatur, Bd. 129), S. 59–75.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Hunston, Susan (2008): <title level="a">Collection strategies and design
                            decisions.</title> In: Anke Lüdeling und Merja Kytö (Hg.): <title>Corpus
                            Linguistics. An International Handbook</title>. 2 Bände. Berlin: De
                        Gruyter (1), S. 154–168.</bibl>
                    <bibl>IFLA (2009): <title>Functional Requirements for Bibliographic
                            Records</title> (Technical Report). Online verfügbar unter
                        http://www.ifla.org/publications/functional-requirements-for-bibliographic-records,
                        zuletzt geprüft am 23.12.2016.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Lüdeling, Anke (2011): <title level="a">Corpora in Linguistics. Sampling
                            and Annotation</title>. In: Karl Grandin (Hg.): <title level="m">Going
                            Digital. Evolutionary and Revolutionary Aspects of Digitization</title>.
                        New York: Science History Publications (Nobel Symposium, 147),
                        220–243.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Moisl, Hermann (2009): <title level="a">Exploratory Multivariate
                            Analysis</title>. In: Anke Lüdeling und Merja Kytö (Hg.): <title>Corpus
                            Linguistics. An International Handbook</title>. 2 Bände. Berlin: De
                        Gruyter (2), S. 874–899.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Winko, Simone (1996): <title level="a">Literarische Wertung und
                            Kanonbildung</title>. In: <title level="m">Grundzüge der
                            Literaturwissenschaft.</title> Hrsg. v. H. L. Arnold und H. Detering.
                        München, 585–600.</bibl>
                    <bibl>van Zundert, Joris; Andrews, Tara L. (2017): <title level="a">Qu'est-ce
                            qu'un texte numérique? A new rationale for the digital representation of
                            text.</title> In: <title level="j">Digital Scholarship in the Humanities
                        </title>(32), S. 78–88. DOI: 10.1093/llc/fqx039.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
