<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="file:/home/lou/Public/TEIslides/teislides.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>Collaborative creation of a multi-lingual literary corpus. </title>
    <title>Challenges and best practices for corpus design</title>
    <author>Lou Burnard</author>
    <author><lb/> Borja Navarro-Colorado</author>
    <author><lb/> Carolin Odebrecht</author>
    <author><lb/> Martina Scholger </author>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <p>unpublished draft</p>
   </publicationStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <p>born digital</p>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2022-04-10">Created file</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>
   <div type="slide">
    <head>ELTeC is a collection; ELTeC-xxx is a corpus</head>
    <list>
     <item>We follow Sinclair (1991) in regarding a <term>corpus</term> as a special kind of
       <term>collection</term> of texts: <eg>“A collection of naturally occurring language text,
       chosen to characterize a state or variety of a language.” <lb/> (John Sinclair, <hi>Corpus,
        Concordance, Collocation</hi>, 1991)</eg></item>
     <item>ELTeC corpora are <emph>designed</emph>, in the sense that their components were chosen
      using explicit selection criteria</item>
     <item>ELTeC corpora are <emph>representative</emph> with respect to those criteria, following Biber
      (1993): <eg>“Representativeness refers to the extent to which a sample includes the full range
       of variability in a population.” <lb/> (Douglas Biber, <hi>Representativeness in Corpus
        Design</hi>, 1993)</eg></item>
     <item>We aim to represent the variety of production and to maximize the variety within each
      time period.</item>
     <item>Hence, the project plan specifies <q>comparable corpora</q>, each providing a <q>balanced
       selection of one hundred novels from the period 1840 to 1920</q></item>
    </list>
    <p rend="box">Easier said than done!</p>
   </div>
   <div type="slide">
    <head>Cross-cultural challenges</head>

    <list>
     <item>Defining candidates of the population we wish to sample : what is a "novel" ?</item>
     <item>Defining the sample : what are the selection criteria ? </item>
    </list>
    <p rend="box">The answers to these questions turn out to be subtly different in different
     cultural contexts... </p>
   </div>
   <div type="slide">
    <head>Our selection criteria</head>
    <list>
     <item>We specified four <q>balance criteria</q> : <list>
       <item>date of first publication in book form</item>
       <item>size in pages</item>
       <item>author gender</item>
       <item>"canonicity" -- operationalised as the number of times a work was republished </item>
      </list></item>
     <item>Criteria we did <emph>not</emph> consider include: <list>
       <item>genre</item>
       <item>topic</item>
       <item>intended readership</item>
       <item>... and many others</item>
      </list></item>
     <item>Partly on practical grounds but also to avoid the risk of circularity: we wanted to make
      it possible to classify texts automatically. </item>
     <item>The goal was to provide good coverage for each criterion, such that the sample would not
      be dominated by any specific author gender or canonicity-value. <list>
       <item>This same concern to avoid bias led us to impose an additional constraint that no more
        than three works should be selected for any given author</item>
      </list></item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="slide">
    <head>What is a novel?</head>
    <list>
     <item>Our definition is fairly broad: <list>
       <item>fictional narrative prose </item>
       <item>first published between 1840 and 1920</item>
       <item>first published in the target language</item>
       <item>of size between 10 and 200 thousand words (so no collected short stories)</item>
       <item>intended for an adult audience</item>
      </list></item>
     <item>But ... <list>
       <item>these criteria effectively ruled out some significant language traditions (e.g. nothing
        or very little of any kind was published in Irish, Latvian, or Lithuanian before
        1900)</item>
       <item>the concepts of “language” and “country” are problematic in the historical European
        context</item>
       <item>the ease with which balance criteria could be satisfied varied greatly across language </item>
       <item>for some criteria, notably author gender, identifying a balanced sample proved
        impossible.</item>
      </list></item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="slide">
    <head>Language is a problem</head>
    <p>The association between languages, countries, and literary traditions is far from being
     unequivocal or simple. </p>
    <list>
     <item>Many European countries (Spain, Switzerland, Belgium, for example) have two or more
      official languages, each with its own publishing tradition. </item>
     <item>In many countries, particularly during the 19th century, the language of culture and
      consequently of publication was not the national language but rather German, French, or
      English. </item>
     <item>The same language or a dialectal variant of it may be found in several different
      countries (Swiss German, or Belgian French, for example). </item>
     <item>Different languages may be considered the cultural norm in different regions of a single
      country (Euskera or Catalan in Spain, for example), and will thus have a claim to be
      represented by their own language corpus.</item>
    </list>
    <p>A pragmatic approach lead us to exclude <list>
      <item>works by non-European authors (e.g. Henry James) </item>
      <item>Works published in a language other than that of their original place of publication
       (e.g. Kafka) </item>
     </list> but to include <list>
      <item>European authors publishing in some language other than their own (e.g. Conrad)</item>
      <item>additional language corpora such as ELTeC-gsw, ELTeC-eus</item>
     </list></p>
   </div>

   <div type="slide">
    <head>Sex is a problem</head>
    <list>
     <item>For some language populations, we have extensive data about male and female authorship. </item>
     <item>For example, the ATCL database lists 22,255 English novels published between 1837 and
      1901, produced by a total of 2067 women, 2497 men, and 623 unknown. </item>
     <item>But this ratio is not consistent over time: </item>
    </list>
    <p>
     <figure>
      <graphic url="media/atclGenders.png" width="90%"/>
      <!-- CO: the figure is  not displayed well. change to 100% or less? -->
      <head>
       <ref target="http://www.victorianresearch.org/atcl/visualizations.php#gender">Bassett, Troy
        J. At the Circulating Library: A Database of Victorian Fiction, 1837–1901. Downloaded from
        http://www.victorianresearch.org/atcl/visualizations.php. </ref>
      </head>
     </figure>
    </p>
    <list>
     <item>In the ELTeC samples, we know that for some languages, the proportion of female/male
      authors never rises above 10% </item>
    </list>
    <p> <figure>
      <graphic url="media/gender.png" width="80%"/>
     </figure></p>
   </div>
   <div type="slide">
    <head>Visualising cultural difference</head>
    <figure>
     <graphic url="media/engHun.png"/>
    </figure>

    <p>Do these variations indicate real cultural differences, or are they a consequence of sampling
     bias?</p>
   </div>
   <div type="slide">
    <head>Visualising cultural difference</head>
    <figure>
     <graphic url="media/deuRom.png"/>
     <graphic url="media/fraPor.png"/>
    </figure>
    <p>Do these variations indicate real cultural differences, or are they a consequence of sampling
     bias?</p>
   </div>
   <div>
    <head>ELTeC Levels</head>
    <p>At the start of the project, the concept of <term>level</term> was introduced to characterize
     the richness of the TEI encoding or annotation applied to an ELTeC text. <list>
      <item>level 0 : only a bare minimum of features are distinguished by the markup </item>
      <item>level 1 : some additional semantic features are marked up</item>
      <item>level 2 : additional annotation of linguistic features (pos code, NER etc.)</item>
     </list></p>
    <p>In practice almost all ELTeC texts are marked up at level 1, with a high degree of
     consistency as to which TEI elements are used and in what context. </p>
    <p>The definition of a schema for level 2 texts proved more problematic, for a variety of
     reasons, both personal and technical.</p>
   </div>

   <div type="slide">
    <head>The ELTeC Corpus Composition Criteria Compliance Calculator</head>
    <list>
     <item>The E5C is an online tool developed in order to assess objectively the degree of
      compliance for each corpus. </item>
     <item>The overall goals of our corpus composition criteria are: <list>
       <item> to achieve some level of comparability between corpora; </item>
       <item> to help maximize the variety of novels we make available, particularly novels outside
        the traditional canon</item>
       <item> to support a certain number of key methods of text analysis. </item>
      </list></item>
     <item>The E5C defines minimal acceptable and optimal values for each of the following: <list>
       <item>Encoding level (either 0 or 1; if both are used, a given title can only appear
        once)</item>
       <item>Number of texts: 100 </item>
       <item>Author gender: at least 10% female, optimally 30% to 50%</item>
       <item>Reprint count: at least 30% "low", optimally 40% to 60%</item>
       <item>Time slot : divided as evenly as possible, i.e. each of the four time slots should
        contain 20% to 25% of the available titles</item>
       <item>Size : at least 20% of titles should be short (10-50k) and at least 20% should be long
        (over 100k). </item>
       <item>Novels per author: to maximize variation, no author should be represented by more than
        3 novels; up to 11 authors may be represented by exactly 3 novels.</item>
      </list>
      <!--<list>
      <item>https://github.com/distantreading/WG1/wiki/E5C-discussion-paper</item>
      </list>--></item>
     <item>The E5C gives an overall score for a corpus: values below 50 indicate issues that need to
      be addressed before the corpus can be included in an ELTeC Release. </item>
     <item>An <term>extension corpus</term> may be used to hold otherwise eligible novels which
      cannot be included without distorting the overall corpus balance, or to build up comparable
      collections outside the scope of ELTeC proper.</item>
    </list>
   </div>


   <div type="slide">
    <head>State of play</head>
    <list>
     <item>There are 17 distinct ELTeC corpora (Czech, German, English, French, Swiss German,
      Croatian, Hungarian, Italian, Norwegian, Polish, Portuguese, Romanian, Slovenian, Spanish,
      Serbian, Swedish, and Ukrainian); in total about 107 million words. </item>
     <item>Only five of these have an E5C score below 75%</item>
     <item>Ten of them are also marked up to level 2 (German, English, French, Hungarian, Norwegian, Portuguese, Romanian, Slovenian, Spanish, Serbian)</item>
     <item>All corpora are available online from gitHub, 12 of them as validated releases from
      Zenodo <ref target="https://zenodo.org/communities/eltec">ELTeC Community</ref></item>
     <item>Summary and other information at <ref target="https://distantreading.github.io/ELTeC"
       >https://distantreading.github.io/ELTeC</ref>
     </item>
     <item>Coming soon: access via <ident>txm</ident>, <ident>gams</ident>, <ident>TEI
       Publisher</ident> ... </item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="slide">
    <head>The future</head>
    <list>
     <item>ELTeC as a well-tested benchmark for the development of literary corpora</item>
     <item>The "extension" concept reapplied to corpora, such as eltec-fra-ext, which use a
      different date-range </item>
      <item>Further languages may be added to ELTeC or as ELTeC extensions</item>
     <item>And maybe also corpora of to other literary forms, such as 19th c. drama</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="slide">
    <head>Conclusions</head>
    <list>
     <item>We learned a great deal about collaboration, about the complexities of cross-cultural
      comparisons, about finding an appropriate technologies for literary studies ... and about the
      European novel!</item>
     <item>We suggest that any effective computational infrastructure for literary studies will need
      to follow our example, if only in the creation of shared textual resources </item>
    </list>
    <p>
     <graphic url="media/finis.png" width="50%"/>
    </p>
   </div>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
