<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Building the ELTeC</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Unpublished source: prepared for Budapest Training school September 2019</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>No source: this is a born digital document</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2019-05-12">LB merge TS Wiki page with index page from Wburg</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="slide">
            <head>Budapest Training School, 23-25 September 2019</head>
            <p>The aim of the Training School is to give participants hands-on experience in
               creating ELTeC TEI-XML versions of source texts starting from scanned page images or
               from a pre-existing HTML version. We will supply a set of raw materials for
               candidates to work on, along with detailed instructions. At the end of the Training
               School, each participant should be able to contribute new TEI encoded texts to the
               ELTeC GitHub repository. Participants will work in pairs with guidance from Martina,
               Carolin, Christian and Lou. </p>
            <p> On Monday, participants will learn how to use Oxygen for encoding texts in TEI XML,
               and will be introduced to the sampling and balance criteria as well as other metadata
               requirements for ELTeC. On Tuesday, they will work with two different transformation
               scenarios for creating TEI XML texts, firstly starting from page images, and secondly
               starting with HTML. We will also discuss the different encoding levels provided for
               ELTeC texts, including proposals for encoding linguistic analysis. In the closing
               sessions on Wednesday, participants will be asked to present what they have achieved,
               and discuss the outcomes of this and other parallel workshops. </p>
            <p> The Training School is intended for any researcher interested in contributing texts
               to the ELTeC. Some previous experience of computer use is needed, but no knowledge of
               TEI XML is assumed. </p>
            <list type="gloss">
               <label>Local Organizers:</label>
               <item/>
               <label>Trainers:</label>
               <item>Christian Reul, Carolin Odebrecht, Martina Scholger, and Lou Burnard </item>
               <label>Participants: </label>
               <item/>
               <label>Location:</label>
               <item/>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="slide">
            <head>Creating texts for ELTeC</head>
            <p>In this workshop you'll learn: <list>
                  <item>what TEI XML markup is and why we use it for the ELTeC</item>
                  <item>how ELTeC texts should be marked up, at levels 0 and 1</item>
                  <item>some practical ways of creating ELTeC texts starting from other formats,for
                     example : <list>
                        <item>plain text output by an OCR system</item>
                        <item>digital documents created with Word or Open Office</item>
                        <item>ePub or HTML documents found on the internet</item>
                     </list></item>
               </list></p>
            <p>You should have some previous experience of working with digital documents, for
               example creating web pages, or editing documents with Word, but you are not expected
               to know anything about TEI or XML! </p>
            <p>Almost all the practical work will be done using <ref
                  target="https://www.oxygenxml.com/xml_editor/download_oxygenxml_editor.html"
                  >oXygen XML Editor</ref>. If you don't already have it installed, you may like to
               download an evaluation copy of this software before the workshop. </p>
            <p>You will also need your own copy of the sample files we will be working with.
               Download them by clicking <ref target="work.zip">this
               link</ref><!--, 
                  or by checking out <ref target="">this github repository</ref>-->.
            </p>
         </div>
        
         <div type="slide">
            <head>Provisional Programme (subject to revision) </head>
            <list>
               <label>Monday</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>Early afternoon: Joint opening session (30 minutes) </item>
                     <item>Afternoon session 1: Introduction to Oxygen and XML (Martina) </item>
                     <item>Afternoon session 2: Metadata (Carolin)</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <label>Tuesday</label>
               <item><list>
                      <item>Morning session 1: Creating OCR with OCR4all (Christian) </item>
                     <item>Morning session 2: Transforming plain text to level0 (Christian and Lou) </item>
                     <item>Afternoon session 1: Transforming Abbyy Outputs to level0 (Lou) </item>
                     <item>Afternoon session 2: Level1, publishing at GitHub, additional
                        enrichment (talk from WG2?) [who?]</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <label>Wednesday</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>Morning session 1: Concluding session (1h) </item>
                     <item>Morning session 2: Joint final session (2 hours)</item>
                  </list>
                 </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
