<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Creating ELTeC</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Unpublished source: prepared for Budapest Training school September 2019</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>No source: this is a born digital document</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2019-05-12">LB merge TS Wiki page with index page from Wburg</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="slide">
            <head>Budapest Training School, 23-25 September 2019</head>
            <p>The aim of the Training School is to give participants hands-on experience in
               creating ELTeC TEI-XML versions of source texts starting from scanned page images or
               from a pre-existing HTML version. We will supply a set of raw materials for
               candidates to work on, along with detailed instructions. At the end of the Training
               School, each participant should be able to contribute new TEI encoded texts to the
               ELTeC GitHub repository. Participants will work in pairs with guidance from Martina,
               Carolin, Christian and Lou. </p>
            <p> On Monday, participants will learn how to use Oxygen for encoding texts in TEI XML,
               and will be introduced to the sampling and balance criteria as well as other metadata
               requirements for ELTeC. On Tuesday, they will work with two different transformation
               scenarios for creating TEI XML texts, firstly starting from page images, and secondly
               starting with HTML. We will also discuss the different encoding levels provided for
               ELTeC texts, including proposals for encoding linguistic analysis. In the closing
               sessions on Wednesday, participants will be asked to present what they have achieved,
               and discuss the outcomes of this and other parallel workshops. </p>
            <p> The Training School is intended for any researcher interested in contributing texts
               to the ELTeC. Some previous experience of computer use is needed, but no knowledge of
               TEI XML is assumed. </p>

            <table>

               <row>
                  <cell>Monday</cell>
                  <cell>time</cell>
                  <cell>Topics</cell>
                  <cell>Learned</cell>
                  <cell>Trainer</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>13:30-14:00 </cell>
                  <cell>30 min</cell>
                  <cell>Joint Opening Session</cell>
                  <cell>what our Action is about and the tasks of the WGs</cell>
                  <cell>Carolin</cell>
               </row>

               <row>
                  <cell>14:00-15:45</cell>
                  <cell> 105 min</cell>
                  <cell> Introduction to Oxygen and TEI XML </cell>
                  <cell> basic XML structure (elements, attributes, hierarchy) and how to use oxygen </cell>
                  <cell> Martina </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell> 16:15-16:45</cell>
                  <cell> 30 min</cell>
                  <cell> Introduction to ELTeC</cell>
                  <cell> what ELTeC is about, Design/Goals, first introduction about components
                     (metadata, encoding) </cell>
                  <cell>Carolin </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>16:45-17:45</cell>
                  <cell> 60 min </cell>
                  <cell>First practical session </cell>
                  <cell> everyone chooses a text (not necessarily one of ours) and creates a header
                     for it: <ref
                        target="http://distantreading.github.io/Training/Budapest/tutorial-hdr.html"
                        >slides</ref></cell>
                  <cell> Lou </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>17:45-18:00</cell>
                  <cell> 15 min </cell>
                  <cell>Github practice. </cell>
                  <cell> Everyone adds their chosen header to their own github repo. </cell>
                  <cell> </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>9:00-10:45 </cell>
                  <cell> 105 min </cell>
                  <cell>Introduction to OCR with OCR4all</cell>
                  <cell> practical and the theoretical background reduced to the minimum, introduce
                     the workflow, then only very briefly explain the individual modules, and the
                     rest of the time we will play around, short discussion advantages and
                     disadvantages of ABBYY and OCR4all (not a presentation of ABBY) generate plain
                     text files from the material</cell>
                  <cell>Christian </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>11:15-13:00</cell>
                  <cell> 105 min </cell>
                  <cell>Working with OCR </cell>
                  <cell> Second practical: everyone chooses a different Polish text <ref
                        target="http://distantreading.github.io/Training/Budapest/tutorial-pol.html"
                        >slides</ref></cell>
                  <cell>Lou</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>13:00-14:00</cell>
                  <cell> 60 min </cell>
                  <cell>LUNCH</cell>
                  <cell> </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>14:00-14:45</cell>
                  <cell> 45 min </cell>
                  <cell>Varieties of markup and conversion tools (talk/discussion)</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <ref
                        target="https://distantreading.github.io/Training/Budapest/formatsTalk.html"
                        >slides</ref></cell>

                  <cell>Lou </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>14:45-16:30</cell>
                  <cell> 105 min </cell>
                  <cell>Working with other OCR outputs (Abbyy xml ─ docx -- HTML ) </cell>
                  <cell> Third practical: everyone chooses a different text <ref
                        target="http://distantreading.github.io/Training/Budapest/tutorial-abbyy.html"
                        > slides</ref></cell>
                  <cell>Lou </cell>

               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>16:30-17:00</cell>
                  <cell> 30 min</cell>
                  <cell>Summary - what have we learned? </cell>
                  <cell> Carolin </cell>
                  <cell> </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>17:15-18:45</cell>
                  <cell>Katherine Bode Lecture </cell>
                  <cell> </cell>
                  <cell> </cell>
                  <cell> </cell>
                  <cell> </cell>
               </row>

               <row>
                  <cell>9:00-10:45 </cell>
                  <cell> 105 min </cell>
                  <cell>Concluding session </cell>
                  <cell> create presentation of the outputs of the workshop, upload data </cell>
                  <cell>Lou, Martina, Christian, Carolin</cell>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>11:15-12-45</cell>
                  <cell>90 min Joint final session</cell>
                  <cell>Lou, Martina, Christian, Carolin</cell>
               </row>
            </table>
            <list type="gloss">
               <label>Local Organizers:</label>
               <item/>
               <label>Trainers:</label>
               <item>Christian Reul, Carolin Odebrecht, Martina Scholger, and Lou Burnard </item>
               <label>Participants: </label>
               <item/>
               <label>Location:</label>
               <item/>
            </list>
         </div>

      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
