<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="file:/home/lou/Public/TEIslides/teislides.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>ELTeC Tutorial</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Publication information</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Information about the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="slide">
                <head>Quick ELTeC Corpus Building</head>
                <p>We've found a great resource on the internet: 100 transcribed Polish novels, all
                    ready to be used. Just a few problems: <list>
                        <item>No metadata (other than filenames), so we need to build a proper ElTeC
                            header for each one</item>
                        <item>No markup of any sort, so we need to identify chapters, headings, and
                            paragraphs automatically if possible</item>
                    </list></p>
                <p>This tutorial steps you through the process of going from a plain text file to a
                    level-0 encoded ElTeC conformant version You should be able to carry this out
                    without any knowledge of Polish, though we do have a Polish participant who has
                    kindly agreed to provide advice if you get stuck. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="slide">
                <head>The recipe</head>
                <p>This is a five stage process</p>
                <list>
                    <item>select and identify the text; create a new empty ELTeC-0 document</item>
                    <item>complete the TEI Header for your chosen title</item>
                    <item>insert the text of the corresponding file into the <gi>body</gi>
                        element</item>
                    <item>identify chapter divisions and chapter titles</item>
                    <item>identify paragraphs</item>
                </list>
            </div>
            <div type="slide">
                <head>Stage 1 : selecting and creating a document</head>
                <p>Take a look at the <ident>POL</ident> folder. It contains 18 files we've
                    pre-selected for you, along with a tiny bit of metadata in a file called
                        <ident>titles.txt</ident> which supplies you with an identifier, a filename,
                    a wordcount, and a magic incantation (see below) for each title. Choose a title
                    to work on (or we'll give you one)! </p>
                <p>Each filename contains the surname of the author, a word from the title, and the
                    date of first publication. You'll need to enter the name and the title in some
                    suitable search engine (Wikipedia, Worldcat ...) to get the metadata necessary
                    to complete your TEI Header, notably the author's full name, dates, and sex, as
                    well as the full title. Armed with that additional information for your chosen
                    text, proceed as follows: </p>
                <list>
                    <item>Open oXygen and click on the New icon (first left on the toolbar); or
                        select File->New from the menu; or type CTRL-N</item>
                    <item>The New File dialogue appears. Under the heading <ident>Global
                            templates</ident>, you should see the template for ELTeC-0. Select it.
                        (If it's not there, you need to tweak your installation of oXygen; or you
                        can simply open the template file <ident>ELTeC-0.xml</ident> from your Work
                        directory). Change the filename in the bottom of the window from
                            <ident>Untitled.xml</ident> or <ident>ELTeC-0</ident> to something more
                        appropriate: we suggest using the identifier for the file you're planning to
                        work on, e.g. POL001. Either way...</item>
                    <item>... the main oXygen editing window opens, with the beginnings of an ELTeC
                        XML file in it. Note the following: <list>
                            <item>At the top of the file there are two purple lines beginning
                                    <code>&lt;?xml-model</code>.</item>
                            <item>The file contains tags (in blue) and attribute names (in orange)
                                but no text as yet.</item>
                            <item>To the right of the main window there is a status bar with an
                                angry red square at the top and some red error flags. These
                                correspond with parts of the text display underlined in red.</item>
                            <item>Underneath the editing window there is an error message
                                corresponding with the first error flag: <code>value of attribute
                                    "xml:id" is invalid; must be an XML name without colons
                                </code></item>
                        </list></item>
                    <item>The red flags tell us that although oXygen has done its best some
                        additional information is needed to create a document which is valid. Let's
                        fix up some of these errors and complete the header!</item>
                </list>
            </div>
            <div type="slide">
                <head>Stage 2 : completing the header</head>
                <list>
                    <item>The schema requires a proper value for @xml:id but we have not yet
                        supplied one. Put the cursor between the quote marks and type in the
                        identifier for your novel, e.g. <code>POL002</code> if you've chosen to work
                        on <ident>beczkowska_bedzie_1897.txt</ident>. A new error message appears!
                            <code>element "TEI" missing required attribute "xml:lang"</code>. </item>
                    <item>Put the cursor before the &gt; at the end of the <gi>TEI</gi> start-tag
                        and type a space to see the available attributes. <att>xml:lang</att>
                        appears in the list in bold because it's required here. Select it, and then
                        add its value (<code>po</code>) to specify the language code for your
                        document. </item>
                    <item>The next red line is complaining about the content of the <gi>measure</gi>
                        element at line 17, which should contain a number. Choose the appropriate
                        word count from the <ident>titles.txt</ident> file (37401 for text POL002)
                        and type it in (note that this is content of an element, not an attribute
                        value)! </item>
                    <item>The next three red lines are all to do with the text classification codes.
                        You need to decide what value to enter for the "authorGender" category (M,
                        F, or U); what size code corresponds with the word count ('short', 'medium',
                        or 'long'); and what time slot code (T1,T2,T3 or T4) is applicable. You have
                        the data: refer to the header documentation (for example <ref
                            target="https://github.com/distantreading/WG1/wiki/teiHeaders">on the
                            wiki</ref>) for a reminder on what the codes mean.</item>
                    <item>To remove tthe only remaining red line in the header, enter today's date,
                        in the right (YYYY-MM-DD) format as value for the <att>when</att> attribute.
                        Phew! no red marks anywhere in the Header -- which is now therefore valid:
                        click the disk icon (or type CTRL-S, or choose File-Save from the menu) to
                        save it for further work. </item>
                    <item>This is a good start, but validity is not necessarily the same thing as
                        truth, and we would prefer our document to be true -- the title of this work
                        is definitely not <code>Title</code>, and your name is not <code>Your Name
                            Here</code>! More seriously, we have not yet provided any information at
                        all about the source from which this ELTeC text derives nor about its
                        author. Over to you... Referring to the <ref target="checkList-1.pdf"
                            >checklist of information needed</ref> and the metadata you accumulated
                        in the first part of this exercise, you should now add the following: <list>
                            <item>the actual title of the novel</item>
                            <item>the author's name and dates in the recommended format</item>
                            <item>an additional <gi>respStmt</gi> to show who was responsible for
                                the original data capture of this title (if you know)</item>
                            <item>the date of publication of this digital version (today!)</item>
                            <item>information about the source as described below</item>
                        </list></item>
                    <item>The source description should contain two <gi>bibl</gi> elements, one
                        (with <att>type</att>
                        <code>digitalSource</code>) for the digital source from which your version
                        derives, and one (with <att>type</att>
                        <code>firstEdition</code>) for the first print edition of this work. Without
                        a lot of detective work, it's hard to tell whether this text was transcribed
                        from the first edition, or via some intermediate modern edition, but if you
                        are reasonably sure that a modern edition is the actual source, you could
                        supply a third <gi>bibl</gi> with information about it.</item>
                    <item> We do know that the text is derived from the digital collection of
                            <title>100 Polish Novels</title> prepared by
                        <!--Jan Rybicki and Maciej Eder
                        of -->the
                        Computational Stylistics Group in Krakow, and that it is freely available
                        from their GitHub repository at
                        https://github.com/computationalstylistics/100_polish_novels. So your first
                            <gi>bibl</gi> might look like this:
                        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><bibl type="digitalSource">
                                <title>100 Polish Novels</title>
                                <respStmt>
                                    <resp>Transcription</resp>
                                    <name>Computational Stylistics Group (Krakow)</name>
                                </respStmt>
                                <ref
                                    target="https://github.com/computationalstylistics/100_polish_novels"
                                /></bibl></egXML>
                    </item>
                    <item>Your research should have provided you with enough information to provide
                        a basic bibliographic description of the first edition of the novel,
                        including for example publisher name, place of publication, as well as the
                        original published title and form of the author's name, which might differ
                        from the versions in use today. At the very least, your <tag>bibl
                            type="firstEdition"</tag> should contain a <gi>date</gi> giving the year
                        of first publication. </item>
                </list>
            </div>
            <div type="slide">
                <head>Stage 3 : add some text</head>
                <p>Now we are ready to add some text to our document. </p>
                <list>
                    <item>put the cursor inside the solitary <gi>p</gi> contained by the
                            <gi>body</gi> element. </item>
                    <item>select Document-> File -> Insert File from the menu, and navigate to the
                        text file you are planning to convert</item>
                    <item>Press Open, and the content of the file is inserted into your document.
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p>Note that the error message <code>The body of a text must contain at least one
                        chapter</code> is still present. We will need to introduce more markup. We
                    could do this slowly and painfully, one step at a time, but computers are
                    supposed to make it easier to automate tasks which are slow and painful. In the
                    next section, we'll see how you can take advantage of any systematic patterns in
                    the format of a non-marked-up text to introduce explicit XML markup. To do this
                    we'll use the sophisticated Find/Replace tools built into oXygen. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="slide">
                <head>Stage 4 : identify the chapters and headings</head>
                <p>To begin, open the <ident>Find/Replace</ident> dialogue and make sure that the
                    check box <ident>Regular expression</ident> is selected. A <term>regular
                        expression</term> is a kind of pattern: the find and replace command usually
                    searches for specific character strings; when regular expressions are enabled,
                    it can also search for complex patterns of characters.</p>
                <p>For example, in some of our Polish texts, every new chapter begins with a roman
                    number on a line of its own. In other texts the chapter number is preceded by
                    the word <code>Rozdział</code>; in yet others the chapter has a title given in
                    uppercase letters only. We can write regular expressions to cater for all of
                    these possibilities. Without regular expression matching, we could seek lines
                    containing the explicit strings I, II, III, IV etc. But it is much simpler to
                    seek all such lines by means of a regular expression matching any sequence of
                    one or more of the letters I V or X followed by a new line. </p>
                <list>
                    <item>In file POL001 for example, each chapter is prefixed by a line containing
                        an uppercase Roman number, followed by a line containing the chapter title,
                        all in uppercase. We can use this regular expression to find these:
                            <code>\n[IXV]+\n[\s\p{Lu}]+\S\n</code>.</item>
                    <item>In file POL007, however, each chapter is prefixed by the word ROZDZIAŁ,
                        followed by one or more spaces, followed by a roman number and a full stop,
                        and a new line. Here's a regular expression which will find these :
                            <code>ROZDZIAŁ\s+[IVX]+\.</code></item>
                    <item>In file POL014, chapters always begin with a lines containing a sequence
                        of uppercase letters and spaces. Here's a regular expression which will find
                        them: <code>[\p{Lu}\s]+\n</code>
                    </item>
                    <item>Of course, in some cases, for example POL004 or POL006, we can't easily
                        identify where new chapters begin, or they may not be marked at all. Where
                        we can however we've included a suggested regular expression in the
                            <ident>titles.txt</ident> file (that's what the mysterious incantantion
                        after the word count is)</item>
                </list>
                <p>The real power of regular expression matching is not just that it enables us to
                    find quickly particular strings in the text. It also allows us to specify
                    replacements for those strings. In our case, wherever we identify something
                    which is the heading of a chapter, we need to tag it as a <gi>head</gi>, and
                    also show that it begins a new chapter by inserting a <tag>div
                        type="chapter"</tag> tag, and (to ensure our document remains well-formed
                    XML) preceding it with a <tag>/div</tag> tag to close the preceding chapter. The
                    syntax for doing this is simple enough: within the replacement part of the
                    find/replace dialogue can contain numbered references (like this :
                        <code>\1</code>) which are to be expanded by a part of the matched string,
                    specifically the part enclosed in parentheses. </p>
                <p>This is easier to understand with an example. Let's suppose you are working on
                    POL001.</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Open the <ident>Find/Replace</ident> dialogue by typing CTRL-F or
                        selecting Find->Find/Replace from the main menu, and type the incantation
                            <code>\n([IVX]+)\n([\s\p{Lu}]+)\S\n</code> carefully into the Find box.
                        Press the <ident>Find</ident> button to check that it is finding what you
                        expect: you should see that the lines <code>I</code> and
                            <code>ALKHADAR</code> have been selected. </item>
                    <item>Each time you press Find, oXygen will step through the file selecting any
                        line containing just a sequence of one or more I X V characters followed by
                        a line containing any sequence of uppercase letters. Try it, just to check.
                        When you're satisfied the regexp is working correctly, move the cursor back
                        to the start of the file and find the first chapter again. </item>
                    <item>The parentheses in your regexp allow us to pick out the two character
                        strings that have been matched, for use in the replacement value. Type the
                        following into the <ident>Replace With</ident> dialogue
                            <code><![CDATA[ \n</div><div type="chapter"><head>\1</head>\n<head>\2</head>\n]]></code>
                        Press the Replace button. You should now see something like this at the
                        start of your file:
                        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><![CDATA[<body>
        <p>Michał Bałucki 
            PRZEBUDZENI
            </div><div type="chapter"><head>I</head>
                <head>ALKHADAR</head>
                Warszawo! niewolnico! kiedyś ....]]></egXML>
                    </item>
                    <item>(The <tag>/div</tag> is underlined in red since there's no chapter to
                        close here. Never mind, we'll fix that later)</item>
                    <item>When you are sure that your regexp is working correctly, press the
                            <ident>Replace to End</ident> button to repeat this manoeuvre for the
                        whole of the rest of the file. You should find 23 matches, and the Outline
                        view (Select Window -> Show view -> Outline if this is not open) should show
                        that you now have 23 chapters. </item>
                </list>
            </div>
            <div type="slide">
                <head>Stage 5: identify the paragraphs</head>
                <p>In this file, every line other than those beginning with a &lt; character now
                    contains a single paragraph. We can use a simple regexp to mark them all up as
                        <gi>p</gi> elements : </p>
                <list>
                    <item>type <code>\n([^&lt;].+)</code> into the <ident>Find</ident> box, and
                            <code>\n&lt;p>\1&lt;/p></code> into the <ident>Replace with:</ident>
                        box.</item>
                    <item>Move the cursor to the start of the file and check that this regexp does
                        what you expect</item>
                    <item>Click the <ident>Replace to End</ident> button as before. There should be
                        about 1994 matches and your task is almost complete!</item>
                    <item>Finally, go back to the start of the document and delete the lines before
                            <tag>div type="chapter"</tag>, including the redundant <tag>/div</tag>.
                        Your file is valid! </item>
                </list>
                <p>Of course, there's still work to be done... we have not tried to deal with the
                    occasional piece of verse, nor have we tried to markup the trailing headings at
                    the end of some divisions, so these are all appearing as spurious <gi>p</gi>
                    elements. Feel free to continue perfecting this text -- or maybe you'd rather
                    try a different one? Congratulations on getting this far! </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
