<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Training school on OCR and TEI for the production of ELTeC</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Unpublished source: prepared for Wurzburg Workshop, April 2018</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>No source: this is a born digital document</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2018-04-19">LB add page for ocr day</change>
         
         <change when="2018-03-22">LB add header; confirm timetable</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="slide">
            <head>Würzburg Training School, 16-17 April 2018</head>
            <p>This two-day Training School is about Optical Character Recognition and Text Encoding
               for the production of ELTeC (European Literary Text Collection) contributions. The
               ELTeC will contain a principled sample of European literary production, containing
               the full text of novels in each of many European languages published between 1850 and
               1920. </p>
            <p>The aim of the Training School is to enable a group of Action participants to go from
               a novel in the form of a scanned book to a TEI-encoded full-text version of the
               novel. </p>
            <p>The target audience are researchers from participating countries interested in
               contributing texts to the ELTeC but who need to digitize texts for this purpose and
               who are insufficiently familiar with the practicalities of Optical Character
               Recognition for full-text generation and with the fundamentals of using the
               Guidelines of the Text Encoding Initiative to do so.</p>
            <list type="gloss">
               <label>Local Organizers:</label>
               <item>Leonard Konle and Fotis Jannidis (University of Würzburg)</item>
               <label>Trainers:</label>
               <item>Christian Reul, Leonard Konle, and Lou Burnard </item>
               <label>Participants: </label>
               <item>Jelena Andonovski (University of Belgrade);
 Alex Ciorogar (UBB Cluj-Napoca);
 Simon Gabay (University of Neuchatel);
 Meliha Handzic (Burch University, Sarajevo);
 Magdalena Krol (Institute of Polish Language, Polish Academy of Sciences);
 Ioana Lionte (University of Iasi);
 Anna Rehorkova (Charles University, Prague);
 Floriana Sciumbata (Universita Trieste);
 Anna Maria Sichani (Kings Digital Lab, London);
 Adeliana Silva (Nova University of Lisbon);
 Andrejka Zejn (Slovenian Academy of Sciences and Arts).
</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="slide">
            <head>Day One : Optical Character Recognition</head>
            <list>
               <item>Introduction : OCR basics and Hands-on with Abbyy FineReader, by Leonard Konle
                  (University of Wurzburg)</item>
               <item><ref target="https://distantreading.github.io/Training/ocr4all_reul.pdf"
                     >OCR4all</ref> : talk and demonstration of OCR4ALL: an open source tool
                  providing a full OCR Workflow, by Christian Reul and Frank Puppe (University of
                  Würzburg)</item>
               <item>
                  <ref target="https://distantreading.github.io/Training/CNC_AR_Wurzburg_TS.pdf"
                     >Digitization practice in the Czech National Corpus</ref>: talk by Anna
                  Řehořková (Charles University)</item>
            </list>
            <p>Location : Philosophische Fakultät, Room 6.E.8, <ref
                  target="https://goo.gl/maps/Lx7B3dRRpMs">Googlemaps</ref></p>
         </div>
         <div type="slide">
            <head>Day Two: creating marked up texts</head>
            <p>In this one day workshop you'll learn: <list>
                  <item>what TEI XML markup is and why we use it for the ELTeC</item>
                  <item>how ELTeC texts should be marked up, at levels 0 and 1</item>
                  <item>some practical ways of creating ELTeC texts starting from other formats,for
                     example : <list>
                        <item>plain text output by an OCR system</item>
                        <item>digital documents created with Word or Open Office</item>
                        <item>ePub or HTML documents found on the internet</item>
                     </list></item>
               </list></p>
            <p>You should have some previous experience of working with digital documents, for
               example creating web pages, or editing documents with Word, but you are not expected
               to know anything about TEI or XML! </p>
            <p>Almost all the practical work will be done using <ref
                  target="https://www.oxygenxml.com/xml_editor/download_oxygenxml_editor.html"
                  >oXygen XML Editor</ref>. If you don't already have it installed, you may like to
               download an evaluation copy of this software before the workshop. </p>
            <p>You will also need your own copy of the sample files we will be working with.
               Download them by clicking <ref target="work.zip">this
               link</ref><!--, 
                  or by checking out <ref target="">this github repository</ref>-->.
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="slide">
            <head>Provisional Programme (subject to revision) </head>
            <list>
               <item>09h30 :<ref target="oxyTut-1.pdf"> Practical session 1</ref>: Using an XML
                  Editor (oXygen) -- what can we do with it? (45 mins)</item>
               <item>10h15 : <ref target="tei4eltec.html">What is the TEI and why are we using
                     it</ref>? (30 mins) </item>
               <item>10h45 : <hi>coffee break</hi></item>
               <item>11h00 : <ref target="oxyTut-2.pdf">Practical session 2</ref>: creating an ELTeC
                  level 0 text from OCR output (60 mins) </item>
               <item>12h00 : <hi>lunch break</hi></item>
               <item>13h00 : <ref target="eltecSchema.html">Understanding ELTeC</ref>: explaining
                  level 0 and level 1 schemas (30 mins)</item>
               <item>13h30 :<ref target="oxyTut-2.pdf"> Practical session 2 contd</ref>: working
                  with Abbyy outputs (60 mins)</item>
               <item>14h30 : <ref target="eltecHdr.html">Understanding the TEI header</ref> (30
                  mins)</item>
               <item>15h00 : <hi>coffee break</hi></item>
               <item>15h15 : <ref target="oxyTut-3.pdf">Practical session 3</ref>: working on your
                  own (60 mins)</item>
               <item>16h15 : <ref target="conversions.html">Converting from ePub and HTML</ref> :
                  some examples (45 mins)</item>
               <item>17h00 : Open discussion and next steps (30 mins) </item>
            </list>
            <p>Location : Philosophische Fakultät, Room 3.E.3, <ref
                  target="https://goo.gl/maps/Lx7B3dRRpMs">Googlemaps</ref></p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
